# **Kevin Doyle**

775 Old Medford Ave.

Email: kevin@kwdoyle.com Phone: (631) 891-7002 www.kwdoyle.com

Highly motivated, accomplished person with a strong background in Evolutionary Biology and a passion for statistical data analysis and genomic computational research. Have a successful record of simultaneously performing multiple research projects with demonstrated ability to write publication-quality papers. Strong, resourceful teacher able to demonstrate and explain complicated concepts. Proficient in wet and dry and laboratory skills.

#### **Qualifications**:

- Unix Systems
- Algorithm Design

- R
- Python
- Statistical Analysis
- Git / GitHub
- Genomic Data Analysis
- MS Office (Word, Excel)
- Software Complication
- Data Management
- Debugging / Troubleshooting
- Wet Laboratory Skills

### Experience:

# **Rosalind & Codecademy Exercises**

http://rosalind.info. http://codecademy.com

May 2016 - Current

Using Python to complete problems under Rosalind's bioinformatics stronghold category and completing Codecademy course on SQL. Some topics completed thus far are:

- Counting nucleotides and SNPs
- Transcribing and translating DNA
- · Calculating probability of inherited alleles
- · Dynamic programming
- Finding DNA motifs

#### **Hollister Lab of Evolutionary Genomics**

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Aug 2015 - May 2016

Project: Evolution of allopolyploidy in *Arabidopsis thaliana* 

Utilized Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK) best practices pipeline to acquire, organize, and analyze genomic data from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database. Analyzed haplotype variance to infer global patterns of genomic divergence. Tools used were SRA Toolkit, SamTools, Picard Tools, Stampy, GATK, UnifiedGenotyper, HaplotypeCaller, VCFtools, SnpEff.

- Created scripts to enhance existing pipelines to streamline analyses
- Maintained data and documentation organized on unix server
- Utilized GATK, Biopython, & R to analyze variation among individuals

#### Computational Biology Coursework

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Aug 2015 - Dec 2015

Created Python scripts to coincided with lectures pertaining to topics such as sequence alignment (pairwise & multiple), genome assembly, and gene finding using hidden markov models. Course project involved creating functioning code from minimally existing Python code to perform an analysis on the accuracy of the duplication-mutation with complementarity (DMC) algorithm specified in Navlakha & Kingsford 2011 on generating phylogenetic trees using a combination of protein-protein interaction (PPI) networks and genomic data.

# **Biometry Coursework**

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Jan 2015 - May 2015

Rigorously utilized R to perform a wide variety of statistical analyses including linear/nonlinear regression, correlation, generalized linear models, probability distributions, maximum likelihood estimates, hypothesis testing, multiple comparisons analysis, bootstrapping and jackknifeing, data visualization with ggplot, ANOVA/ANCOVA, model selection/comparison, and principal component analysis.

### **Baines Lab of Aquatic Ecology**

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Aug 2013 - May 2016

Project: Fe Limitation in the Copepod Acartia tonsa

Designed an experiment to determine the critical Fe:C threshold where iron limitation occurs in *Acartia tonsa* and performed statistical analyses using R and Excel to find where threshold occurred. Scrupulously clean conditions had to be maintained regarding all reagents and surfaces to prevent trace metal contamination.

- · Maintained organized records of calculations and analyses
- Used R package 'segmented' to estimate where Fe threshold occurred by calculating the breakpoint between two separate linear regressions of egg production with replete Fe and egg production with deplete Fe
- Produced figures with R and Excel
- · Grew cell and zooplankton cultures
- · Created various chemical reagents to use in experiment
- Wrote paper (Estimating the Threshold of Iron Limitation in the Copepod Acartia tonsa) for publication

# Other Experience:

### **Department of Environmental Conservation, Field Technician**

Ridge, NY 11961

May 2016 - September 2016 (Seasonal)

Surveyed historic breeding sites across Long Island to determine the status of tiger salamander (*Ambystoma tigrinum*) and diamondback terrapins (*Malaclemys terrapin*) populations and their respective habitats. Also Assisted in setting up exclosures on piping plover (*Charadrius melodus*) breeding sites.

- Performed atmospheric and water chemistry analyses
- Surveyed ponds for A. tigrinum using dip net and seine
- Used ArcMap data in Google Earth to locate sites
- Entered data using Excel
- Organized project goals & led team to complete daily tasks

#### **Brookhaven National Laboratory, Summer Sunday Tour Guide**

Upton, NY

July 2016 (Seasonal)

Assisted patrons to Brookhaven National Laboratory's Summer Sundays which featured the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider, the National Synchrotron Light Source II, and the Center for Functional Nanomaterials.

## Education:

# **MA Biology - Applied Evolution**

2015

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Relevant coursework: Biometry, Computational Biology, Population Genetics

GPA: 3.8

# **BS Biology - Ecology & Evolution**

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Minor: Ecosystems and Human Impact

Dean's List

Golden Key Honor Society

# Teaching:

# **BIO 341: Plant Diversity — T.A.**

2015

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Description: An introduction to the study of plants, especially green plants, including the origin and evolution of land plants. Topics include cellular structure and function, photosynthesis and respiration, gross anatomy, taxonomy and the diversity of organisms, plant ecology, agriculture.

### SBC 201: Systems and Models - T.A.

2012

Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11790

Description: Introduction to the dynamic modeling of complex systems using simulation software that facilitates the visualization, formulation, and analysis of systems. Systems studied include ecological, economic, chemical, population, and epidemiological models.

2013